Hello,
AP US History students.  Here is the
fifth period in just
4 minutes.  The fifth
period begins in
1844 with the election of
James C. Polk.  He
supported "Manifest
Destiny," which
asserted that it was
God's duty for
America to spread
from coast to
coast.  Polk
campaigned under the
expansionist
slogan "54-40 or war"
and endorsed the annexation of
Texas.  This led
to disputes over
borders along the
Rio Grande River, which
ultimately led to the
Mexican-
American War.
The war ended in
1848 with the Treaty of
Guadalupe Hidalgo, and
America received
present-day Arizona, New
Mexico, Utah, Nevada,
and California.  And
shortly after that,
gold was discovered in California, leading
to the California
Gold Rush.
But all of these new lands
led to debates
about whether to allow
slavery in these new
territories.  Henry
Clay attempted to
ease these
tensions
with the Compromise of
1850.  It
provided for
the admission of
California as a
free state and
popular sovereignty
for Utah and New
Mexico.  And while it
outlawed the
slave trade in Washington,
D.C., it
also strengthened the
Fugitive Slave Act,
which angered
abolitionists.  This
long-running debate over
slavery is the main
focus of the fifth
period.  Harriet
Tubman famously
helped
enslaved people
escape via the
Underground Railroad,
and Harriet Beecher Stowe
published
Uncle Tom's Cabin to
draw attention to the
horrors of slavery.  But
the South responded with
arguments in
defense of slavery, such as
George Fitzgibbon's "Sociology of the South."
Tensions reached a
boiling point in 1854
with the
Kansas-Nebraska Act,
which allowed
popular sovereignty
in the territories of
Kansas and Nebraska.
Supporters and
opponents of slavery
filled these
territories in the hope of
swaying the vote
in their favor.
Violence erupted, and more than 50
people died in
events that became
known as "Bloody
Kansas."  Violence
was also prominent in the
U.S. Senate chamber
during a heated debate
over slavery, when
Southerner Preston
Brooks attacked
Massachusetts Senator Charles
Sumner with his
cane.  The fifth
period also
saw the
controversial decision
in the Dred Scott case of
1857.
Supreme Court Chief Justice
Roger Taney
ruled that
African Americans were not
U.S. citizens and that
Scott had no
constitutional rights.
It also repealed the
Missouri
Compromise.  That same
year, John Brown
attacked
Harpers Ferry in an
attempt
to start an armed
slave uprising.
Southerners considered
him an extremist and
feared the rise of
violent and
radical
abolitionism, while
some Northerners
saw Brown as a
martyr.  These debates
over slavery and
disagreements over
protective tariffs and
states' rights continued
to heighten
tensions between
the North and the South.
All of this culminated
with the election of
Republican
Abraham Lincoln in
1860.  The Southern
states were
convinced that
Lincoln would abolish
slavery and began
to secede from
the Union, forming the
Confederate States of
America.  And when the
shots rang out at
Fort Sumter, the
Civil War officially began.
Although many
Northerners believed
the war would be quick,
it dragged on for
four long years.
The South had better
generals and
dedication to the cause,
but the North ultimately
won the war because it
had money,
infrastructure, a
larger population, and the
leadership of President
Lincoln.  During
the war, Lincoln introduced
conscription, suspended
habeas corpus in
the border states,
and issued the
Emancipation Proclamation,
which prevented the South from
gaining European
support.  After
the war ended in 1865,
America
entered a period
known as
Reconstruction to
bring the former
Confederate states back
into the Union.  And
although President Andrew
Johnson and
Radical
Republicans in
Congress
disagreed over the
best course of action, the
Radicals ultimately
took control of the process
through military
reconstruction.  The Bureau of
Freedmen's Affairs
was one of the
greatest successes of
Reconstruction.  It
provided necessities,
such as food, shelter, and
education, to recently
freed
African Americans.
Congress also
passed amendments to the
Reconstruction-era Constitution.  The 13th
Amendment abolished
slavery, the 14th
defined
citizenship and
guaranteed equal
protection, and the 15th granted the
right to vote to all
men.  This
led to the election of
African Americans to
Congress for the first time in
history, including
Hiram Revels.
However, Reconstruction
had many setbacks.
Although slavery was
abolished, it was
replaced by a
patriarchal
tenancy system that forced
African Americans
to work on
plantations and
fall into
debt.  And southern states
disenfranchised
black voters
using
poll taxes and
literacy tests.
Progress
was also hindered by the emergence of "
black codes,"
Jim Crow laws, and
racist groups such
as the Ku Klux Klan.    The
fifth period
ends with
the Compromise of 1877.
Republican
Rutherford Hayes was
elected president
in exchange for withdrawing
troops from the South, ending
Reconstruction.
Thank you for watching.
If you need
additional help with
APUSH, such as study
guides,
timelines, and summary videos
,
be sure to
check out the "Ultimate
Review Packet."